[SPEAKER_00] Bismillah ar-Rahman ar-Raheem. Mahmoudan wa salni' ala rasulina kareem amma ba'ad. Before we start, can everybody just check their books to see if that's their own book because somebody's book went missing so they're thinking that maybe it got mixed up with somebody else's book. So if you could just check that your book is actually your book. Yeah, there were some books on the podium. So basically, whoever puts their book on the podium, then that book would be theirs. You found it? Oh, okay, somebody else's. Because he has his notes in it, so he was just wondering. Just check, inshallah.
[SPEAKER_00] If you could just... Yeah, okay. I mean, there has to be somebody here that has the book, so if you could just check, please. If it's not your book. All right. If you do find it, if you see Brother Okash's name in it, then please return his book back to him, inshallah. All right. Bismillah ar-Rahman ar-Rahim. Nah'mad abun wa sanii ala Rasulil Kareem. Amma ba'ad. So we left off on lesson four. Inshallah we have a couple lessons to go. We're going to finish that up, inshallah. So in this lesson we started talking about huruf al-jar. Can someone remind me again? What does a harf al-jar do? Makes the next word kasra. Makes the next word kasra. Okay, very good. What are the harf al-jars that we learned so far? Give me one. Fi. What does fi mean?
[SPEAKER_00] In. Okay. Ala. What does Ala mean? On. Ilah. Okay. What does Ilah mean? To. Then? Min. What does Min mean? From. Li. Okay. What does Li mean? For or belongs to. Okay. So in this first part of this fourth lesson, we got introduced to Fi and Ala, which we already did yesterday. Okay. So we finished up to Ein As-Sahe, Al As-Sareer. Where did we get up to yesterday? 22, right? Okay. So let's go to the bottom. We went over also the fact that female names... What's special about female names? Okay, Tamar Buta, but what else? Specifically that we learned in this lesson. No Tanween. Yeah, good. So female names will not have Tanween. Okay? Say, You don't say, Like the Hadith. وَفَاطِمَةُ سَيِّدَةُ
[SPEAKER_00] نِسَائِيَهِ الْجَنَّةِ And Fatima is the leader of the women of Jannah. It comes in some of the Arabic khutbahs that are read. So just a point to note that female names do not have tanween. Do not take tanween. Okay. And we also went over Aina, which is another member of which family? The inquisitive family, yes. أَدْوَاتُ الْإِسْتِفْحَامِ Questioning family. So Aina is used to ask about place So Aina means where What else did we learn? Hua, Dlamir I think we stopped over here We were going to go into Dlamir But then, did we go into it? We did it We did? I took notes We discussed the three things about Oh yeah, we did, you're right So Hua, it means he But we discussed what is a pronoun What is the purpose of a pronoun And we also talked about what Hua indicates towards It indicates towards somebody that's singular, male, and third person.
[SPEAKER_00] We also explain what does third person mean. Can somebody very briefly explain to me what is third person? Somebody we're talking about who's not here. Yes. Somebody who's not in the conversation. I mean, they could technically be even a foot away, but they're not part of the conversation. So in Arabic, that's called ghaib, siratul ghaib. So yeah, that's what it's used for. But we can just say third person. right somebody who's not in the conversation where a second person is what yeah when you're talking to the person you is a second person pronoun wait third person is like he but can't the person also be involved in the conversation just say he how and give me an example if he's right here oh you say he did this he did that he's literally right there listening to you yeah that's That's what I just said, right? If he's not involved in a conversation, meaning you're not directly talking to him. That's what I mean. Get it? You're not talking to that person.
[SPEAKER_00] If you were talking to him, you wouldn't say he, you would say you. Get it? Okay, then first person means what? Everybody seems very dead today. Are you guys tired? Is it the weather? What is it? Pressure. Weather? Pressure? The test pressure? We have a break coming up. You guys already looking forward to the break? Is that what it is? Okay. So, first person, when you're talking about yourself, right? Me, I, or we, right? In Arabic, it would be ana, as we learn later on, inshallah. So, this pronoun over here, hua, is third person. Same thing with hiya. Hiya is also third person. The only difference between hua and hiya is one is male, one is female. So, hiya is for she or... You can also say it, if you're talking about a female object. Yeah, it's the gender neutral, if you want to use those terms.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay, page 22 on the bottom, let's go there. Very quickly, I'm going to read, the only reason I'm reading is because if I was to ask each person to read, unfortunately it would take long, and we don't have the luxury of time right now. So I'm going to read the sentence Correctly with its iraab So just pay attention to how I'm reading it Especially pay attention to the harf al-jar How it's making the next word kasra And I want you guys to translate After I read We're on page 22 at the bottom الطالب في الجامعات Not the boy The student is in the university الطالب is a student الرجل في المسجد Good, the man is in the masjid أين التاجير Where is the merchant or businessman هو في الدكان He is in the shop or a store Good القلم على المكتبي Yes,
[SPEAKER_00] the pen is on the desk أين زينب Just note that it's not زينب It's زينب Where is زينب هي في الغرفة She's in the room Good Ghurfa means room Ayn al-warakoo Where is the paper? Huwa ala al-maktabi It is on the desk We're good Again remember Don't automatically translate Huwa to he Because in certain circumstances It can mean it Depending on what is being referred to So it is on the desk Ayn al-mudarrisu Where is the teacher? Huwa fi al-fasli He is in the classroom Good He is in the classroom He's in the bathroom Where is Yasir? He is in the bathroom or the toilet What was the difference between Hammam and Mirhad As I explained to you Bathroom and shower So Hammam is If you're using colloquial language You're speaking to regular Arabs They'll
[SPEAKER_00] use Hammam for everything If you're actually using the toilet They'll say Hammam But if you want to be technically correct Then Mirhaw is using the actual toilet And Hammam is taking a shower Okay The sun and the moon are in the sky Not where There's no where over here What does man mean? Who In the classroom Who is in the classroom? Okay, good Then this is just a list of male names and female names. Just note that Muhammadun, Tanwin, Khayidun, Tanwin, Hamidun. So again, just remember the general rule is that an ism, a noun will have Tanwin on it. If there's no al, then generally it's going to have Tanwin. There's only certain exceptions. And we just learned one of the exceptions, which is? Which is?
[SPEAKER_00] If it's a female name Not if it's in Tamar Buta Because there's many objects For example Sa'atun That does an tanwin So specifically female names of people So that's an exception of the rule Otherwise generally If it doesn't have al It's going to have tanwin on it But an exception is One exception is female names Another exception is Mudaaf, Mudaafire, which we are going to go to in the next section, inshallah. Okay, so they're just trying to highlight that here. The difference between male names, Muhammadun, Khalidun, Hamidun, Yasirun, Ammarun, Sa'idun, Aliun, Abbasun. And female names, which is Aminatu, Zainabu, Fatimatu, Maryamu, Aishaatu, Khadijaatu, Safiyatu, Ruqayyatu. Okay, everybody got that? Okay, next page, 24. We are introduced to two more harful jars, right? So again, remind me, what does a haraf al-jar do? Makes the
[SPEAKER_00] next word kasra. Okay. Al-baytu, translate. Min al-bayti. Al-masjidu. Ilal-masjidi. To the masjid, good. Not in the masjid. Fi is in. Ilal is to. Okay. Al-mudaris, the teacher. Min aina anta? From where are you? Yeah, where are you from in normal English? If you want to say, from where are you, then you can say that too. Muhammad. I'm from Japan. I am from Japan. Okay, good. And where is Ammar from? He's from China. And where is Hamid from? He's from Hindi. Where is Abbas? Okay, now here is an
[SPEAKER_00] important thing which we learned Which is what? A verb, right? This is the first verb that we learned in this class We only learned basically two verbs in this class Which are? خرجة and ذهب Okay So we all know what a verb is, right? Do I have to explain that again? Remember at one point in one of the first sessions of the class We discussed how in Arabic, words are divided into three different types What were they? Ism, fa'al, and harf So most of what we've been doing so far, they're all ism, they're all nouns There were a few harfs that we did Like harf al-jar, for example, harf al-adwa, wa, is a harf There are a few other, like even a, when we say So that A is also a harf But generally everything else that we did Was all nouns This is the first time We're coming across a verb
[SPEAKER_00] A fi'l Which is No it's in the name right So it's not part of the What is a verb? A verb is something that indicates action. So basically, it indicates action and also in Arabic, specifically, it indicates tense, right? It gives an idea to the time period when something happens. If you just say, for example, desk, does that give you any notion of the time? No, right? You can't tell in which time period you're talking about the desk, right? Whenever you mention a verb, it gives an indication towards time. For example, he went somewhere. When you say went, what does that indicate? Is he going there now? No. It happened in the past. He is going to go somewhere. What does that indicate
[SPEAKER_00] in terms of time? Future. He is going somewhere. Present tense. So the same thing in Arabic. Verbs, they indicate tense. They indicate the time in which that action is occurring. Whereas Asma, generally, again, there's exceptions, but we won't want to go into those yet. But generally, the Ism, the nouns, don't indicate time in any way. So, Kharaja over here. What do we learn from this word Kharaja? The translation is what? He left. Okay. But what are the, I think I mentioned four things that we learned from this specific tense of this verb. Okay, good. First is past tense, okay? This format will be used for the past tense verb generally, right? فَعَلَ ذَهَبَ Give me an example from the Qur'an of a verb that's on this pattern.
[SPEAKER_00] قَتَلَ Yeah, أَنَّهُ مَنْ قَتَلَ نَفْسًا Right? قَتَلَ means he killed, whoever kills, right? Okay, any other example? Yeah, ذهب So ذهب comes in many different places in the Quran فَلَمَّا ذهبَ عَنْ إِبْرَهِمَ الرَّوْ That's going to come right after So the past tense verbs Will be on this pattern generally So one is It's past tense, right? That's one thing فَيَعَ الْمَاضِي Then second What is another thing that this خَرَجَة indicates? Male Okay, it's talking about a male If it was to be female Then it would have been خَرَجَت We're not getting there yet But just to tell you the difference But we're talking about a male So it's خَرَجَ What else does it indicate? Singular If it was dual Meaning if there were two people That were leaving Then it would be خَرَجَ And if there were three or more Plural Then it would be خَرَجُ Like
[SPEAKER_00] in the Quran أَلَمْ تَرَئَ إِلَا الَّذِينَ خَرَجُوا مِنْ دِيَارِهِمْ Have you seen those who left from their homes? Okay, so that would be plural But خرج indicates towards a single person A male, past tense Right, and there's one more thing Third person, good Third person, so it's when you're talking about somebody that's not involved in the conversation If you were talking in second person, meaning you left, right Then you would say خرجت Okay, and if you were talking about first person, meaning I left or we left You would say, خَرَجْتُ or خَرَجْنَا You don't have to worry about this I'm just telling this to you so that we know That verbs change based on all these different things Whether to male or female Whether it's singular, plural or dual And whether it's past tense, present tense, future tense And what was the fourth thing? Third
[SPEAKER_00] person First person, second person or third person So all these things have an effect on the verb And inshallah, sooner or later I know class is fun right now It's starting to get more and more difficult But it's only going to get more difficult unfortunately But inshallah, that's also where it becomes more and more fun Because we start learning even more And understanding more and more of the Qur'an So inshallah, eventually we're going to be learning a chart And memorizing a chart Which helps us to know How to say a verb in each context If you're talking about three males Or you're talking two three males or more We're talking to one female person I know a lot of you are waiting for that one So knowing how to use the verb In all those contexts That inshallah will come soon All right So خراجة means he left Okay أين ذهب Translate Where did he go So ذهب again is Singular Male, masculine Right
[SPEAKER_00] Third person And past tense These are the things we know from this So ذهب He went إلى المدير What does مدير mean? Sorry, sorry أين ذهب means where did he go? ذهب إلى المدير He went to the principal المدير is the principal وَأَيْنَ ذهبَ عَلِيٌ And where did Ali go? ذهب إلى المرحاض So just something Sorry, say it again He went to the toilet So just to note I know we translated as he left and as he went but you don't have to be so literalistic that everywhere it comes I have to translate as he left, he left you have to look in the sentence and see who is it that's doing the leaving so for example you don't translate it as and where he went that doesn't make any sense so you have to use your brain and think okay
[SPEAKER_00] who is doing the leaving It is Ali So now you translate it like that in your head Where did Ali go? Like that Everybody understand that? So that's a mistake some of you were making earlier Just keep that in mind That you should search for This is called a fa'il You don't have to get confused with the terminology for now Insha'Allah that will come But the fa'il is the doer of the verb Right? So you should just think automatically Who is the one who is doing the verb If it's not mentioned in the sentence That's when you say Okay, it's indicated It's implied from the context Who is going For example, Ayn Abbasun was the question. Where's Abbas? The answer was just Kharaja, he left. So in that case, it's implied that it's talking about Abbas who was mentioned previously. You get it? But if a name is mentioned in the sentence, then you will automatically say, okay, that's the fa'al, that's the doer. So you attribute it to him. If it was to say Kharaja Abbasun, you would say Abbas left. You wouldn't say he left Abbas. Just so we understand what we mean when we're translating the verbs. Okay
[SPEAKER_00] So we got that down The verbs down The past tense verbs And من and إلى Okay Okay Alright من أين فاطمة You guys don't feel like Should we just end class You guys tired or something من أين فاطمة هي من الهندي Alright, let's just go to the next lesson Okay, lesson number five Okay, in this lesson One of the important things we learned is مضاف and مضاف إلي Can anybody remind me what مضاف and مضاف إلي is? Yeah, possessor and possessed We did go into some detail about how It's not always necessarily the case But just for the sake of ease of translation We can say possessor and the possessed Okay,
[SPEAKER_00] alright A kitab Muhammadin Hatha, ya Yasir Yes Is this Muhammad's book Oh Yasir Or if you just want to say Yasir Is this Muhammad's book, you can translate it like that as well Okay, so Kitab Muhammadin, this is the thing that we are focusing on here, right? That's the important point over here, okay? Okay, so Kitab-u Muhammadin So one thing we note here, right? is that, remember we mentioned that if Sunni doesn't have Al, then generally it will have what? Tanween, right?
[SPEAKER_00] But over here there's no Tanween, right? So we know that one rule is that the Mudaaf, which is the thing that is being possessed, right? It will not have Tanween, right? Did anybody write down the five rules that we wrote about Mudaaf and Mudaaf, right? Okay, so rule number one is what? Okay, the possessed comes first. or the mudaf comes first. So kitabu, the book of, so that comes first. Then what is the second rule? The possessed never gets al. Okay, possessed never gets al. So over here, it's not al-kitabu muhammadin, it's just kitabu, right? Third rule? Yeah, so the possessor, meaning the mudaf ilayh, What about Tanween? We didn't have that as a rule? Yeah, there's no Tanween also. That's rule number three? Rule two is it doesn't get out of Tanween.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay, yeah. So rule number two is it can never, the Mudaaf can never have Al or Tanween. Okay, Mudaaf can never have Al or Tanween. Everybody understand that, right? We went over it quite a bit. Okay, the third is that Mudaaf ilayh generally will have a Kasra. Alright? Kitabu Allahi, Kitabu Muhammadin. Okay, next Rule Yeah, nothing will come between the Mudaf and the Mudaf Then, last rule Was there any more? Oh yeah, it's not really a rule But it's just so we understand That the Mudaf Which is this first word In this construction Yeah, it doesn't only have to be Dhamma Because most of the examples that we saw here were dhamma So people were thinking automatically that Okay, so the mudhaf has to be dhamma And the mudhaf ilay has
[SPEAKER_00] to be kasra Right, but that is not the case And we've already seen examples of the contrary And somebody give me an example from the Qur'an In which the mudhaf is not dhamma إِنَّ الَّذِينَ يَتْلُونَ كِتَابَ اللَّهِ Right Indeed those who recite the book of Allah Kitab Allah So it's Kitab Allah It's with a Fathah It's with a Zabr Yeah, perfect So it's a Kasra Good, good example It's Kasra It's Mudaf and An-Nas is Mudaf Got it? Okay So those are the Yeah, yeah So, yeah, good point So the reason we were mentioning in rule number three That generally The mudaf ilayh
[SPEAKER_00] will be kasra Because there are exceptions One example is that there are certain Names or certain words That do not change no matter what the context is For example It'll come later on in this same page Kitabu man hadha Right, where is it? قَلَمُ مَنْ هَذَا On the 7th, 8th line or something قَلَمُ مَنْ هَذَا So man is a mudaf ilayh The pen of whom is this So man is mudaf ilayh But man is one of those words that never changes No matter what context it comes in So we shouldn't get confused For example, somebody When he first heard mudaf mudaf ilayh I think it was Brother Jibreel He was so confused I know this is mudaf mudaf ilayh But the second word is not kasra Why? It was kitab Musa وَمِنْ قَبْلِهِ كِتَابُ مُوسَى So it fits everything with Allah, but the only problem is that it's not kasra The second word is not kasra So what is it, right? So the only reason is because Musa never changes no matter what context
[SPEAKER_00] it comes in You can't say مُوسَى يَا مُوسَى يُوء مُوسَى يِي It's just Musa in every single circumstance مِلَّةَ إِبْرَاهِيمَ Yeah, good So مِلَّةَ إِبْرَاهِيمَ That's a little bit different though Because the word Ibrahim does change But it changes in a different way That's an exception that will come I think it's the last lesson in this book It's called غير منصرف Or الممنوع من الصرف But that's another example Of an exception So just know that Don't get too confused or scared When you see something in the Quran Where you know it's مُضَاف مُضَاف إِلَي But the second word is not كَسْرَ Just know that Okay, that's probably one of the exceptions We didn't learn yet I'm not going to worry about it As far as I know As far as I'm concerned The second word The مُضَاف إِلَي Will always have كَسْرَ Okay Alright Okay لا هَذَا كِتَابُ حَمِدٍ No This is the book of Hamid No This is the book of Hamid So just remember that What
[SPEAKER_00] do you call it The easiest way to translate مُضَاف and مُضَافِلَي Is The blank of blank Right Because in some cases When we say Oh If we think like Okay the thing that is being possessed Is first That doesn't always work If you think of it in terms of possession and possessed Remember we had that moment of confusion When we said رَبِّ الْعَالَمِينَ Or like رَبِّ النَّاسِ So that's مُضَافِ مُضَافِ لَي But if we say the possessed is always first Are we saying رَبِّ which is Allah Is the possessed No, right? But we translate it as the Lord of mankind Do you get it? Lord of mankind So if you ever get confused about Oh wait, possess, possessor Don't worry about all that Just have it like systematically in your mind That the first, you just put it as Kitab, okay Book, book of Muhammad Right? Blank of blank Blank of blank Kitab-u Muhammadin The book of Muhammad Qala Muhammadin The pen
[SPEAKER_00] of Hamid Maktab-u Salim The desk of Salim So just make that systematic connection in your mind Insha'Allah you won't get confused With oh what's the possessor What's the possessor Just know that the mudaf is first Mudafi day is second And just think of it as blank of blank Maliki Yawm al-Din For example The owner of the day of judgment You're raising your hands I was going to ask how we know where hada comes up Because the first one hada Comes after the mudafi day For which one? For what you're talking about? Like comparing the first line to the second I don't understand why hada comes up okay so when it when it comes to asking questions the order of things in arabic kind of gets skewed it's obviously in arabic it's not skewed for us and who speak english for us it gets skewed because we get a little confused right um like in english we just say is this muhammad's
[SPEAKER_00] book and an answer would be yes this is hama's book so the order is pretty much the same but in Arabic you're bringing the book first right so like if you want to translate literally it would be like the is the book of Muhammad this right if you want to translate literally but that's obviously not how he would translate in English so just know that generally the thing that you are asking about in Arabic comes first right so you're asking about the book of Muhammad so that's why it's coming first and that's why the Hadha is coming second again it can get a little confusing so you don't really half know this rule but since you were asking about the order that's I think that you also too reading or writing from it it's not that it's this Muhammad's book the book is left it's left it's last now it's backwards now because right to left so the book is first no not necessarily no yeah because when you if you look at the next line then the order is pretty much the same as we would have said in English no this is
[SPEAKER_00] Hamid's book you get it yeah What if you ask that question So basically There's a very slight difference I don't want to confuse you guys So if you're confused on this topic Just shut off your ears for a second But the difference is If you're saying Then it's as if you're saying Is this Muhammad's book Or is something else Muhammad's book You get it? But if you're saying, أَكِتَابُ مُحَمَّدٍ هَذَا Then it's like you're saying, Is this Muhammad's book or is this someone else's book? Do you get the difference? Yes or no? Let's say if it's scramble, you can still be able to decipher which one is which. Even if it's not in order. No, because the order plays a role in that. Okay. Alright. Okay. أَيْنَ كِتَابُ مُحَمَّدٍ
[SPEAKER_00] Where is Muhammad's book? هُوَ عَلَى الْمَكْتَبِ هُنَاكَ Yeah, هُنَاكَ is a new word It is, it means there Okay Did I mention ظَرْف? I think I did, right? That's another family We did, right? I think we did it Check your families If you have them all written down One of the families should be ظَرْف Or ظُرُوف, no? Okay, interesting Okay, so let's just add that now What is it called? Zarf Zarf, if you want to translate it literally It means a container or vessel Right? But in the context of Arabic In the context of grammar It's anything that indicates towards Either place or time Okay? Something that indicates towards either place or time
[SPEAKER_00] Okay So We will learn another Actually it's already here Another dharf is Tahta al maktabi Under the desk So tahta is a dharf Because it indicates towards a place of something Right There's more intricacies Again inshallah all these things we'll learn In much more detail later I'm just introducing you to them now So we have an idea If you don't know this name Don't worry It might be extra credit But you're not going to be Like things like this Small things like this You won't fully be tested on Other things I'm not saying it won't test you On any of the names of families I will test you But this specific one Because I didn't mention it before I may not test you on Or it might be extra credit Sorry? We can if you want Yeah I don't have them all listed But if somebody has them listed We can go through them very quickly Yeah somebody could Brother Salim Inshallah maybe could You can share it on the
[SPEAKER_00] roof also Yeah, yeah, inshallah Yeah, so Okay, so هناك is a ظرف It means there, right? It indicates towards a place There, okay? All right أين دفتر عمار Where is Ammar's notebook? Not office هو على مكتب المدرس He's on teacher's desk Good The pen of whom is this Or whose pen is this Again if you want to make it easier for yourself Even if it sounds awkward in English But the easiest way is to say The blank of blank So the pen of whom is this Ali But if you translate it properly You would say whose pen is this So again this is Even though the second word is not And we explain why that is the case So whose pen is this This is the teacher's
[SPEAKER_00] pen Where is the teacher's bag? Under the desk To test yourself You can do these exercises on yourself again For example They give you two words Qalamun hamidun So make one the mudhaf of the other Mudhaf mudhaf filay, right? So Qalamun hamidun would become Qalamu hamidun Baytun Abbasun would become Let's just go over it very quickly Because this is a very important concept That will definitely be tested Extensively in this test So just make sure mudhaf mudhaf filay is one thing Because I went over it in four lessons And I don't want anybody to not understand mudhaf mudhaf filay Okay? So inshallah that will definitely No matter what be on the test And maybe multiple questions So make sure you know it inside out So let's all read it Very
[SPEAKER_00] very quickly together Qalamun hamidun Qalamun hamidun Baytun abbasun Ghurfatun aliyun Good Daftarun sa'idun Mindeelun yasirun Qamisun ammarun Qamisun ammarun Good Sarirun khalidun Good So again, this type of composition, the blank of blank, should be seared into our brains at this point, right? As soon as you see in the Quran, you should think, oh, wudaf, wudafili, right? Okay. We're
[SPEAKER_00] not going to read all this because we don't have time. These examples, you can go over these examples yourself. Is there a rule we should be applying for exceptions to not make the second one to not make the second one? To make the second one? To make the second one? Oh, what's the rule? Is there a rule that we should be? There are rules, yeah. But at this point, we didn't learn any of the rules yet. It's going to come later on. So that's why I like this book, because a lot of these grammar books, they'll tell you all the exceptions when they're teaching you the rule. And that makes things much more confusing, right? If you're teaching the rule, but you're also teaching the exceptions, then people are going to be like, oh, you know, so like, if you teach the rule as if it's a blanket rule in the beginning, and then later on, once the concept is already solidified, then you mention the exception, then people can be like, okay. But if you mention the exception, why are we going to be like, wait, what? My life is a lie. Like, I thought mudafir is always kasra. And now you're telling me it's not always kasra And you know, it gets very confusing So that's why I like this book Because it gradually introduces everything So those exceptions will come inshallah As time
[SPEAKER_00] comes on Okay What were we doing? Okay, yeah So you can go over these examples Page 28, 29 on your own inshallah All the tamreens will definitely help you Inshallah to solidify everything Sorry, one thing we forgot to mention is Harfun Nida Ya, right? Ya is when you're doing need that when you're calling to someone, right? We said it could be translated as oh, right? Just oh, right? Or you could just not translate it. You could just say, like, as I said, ya yasiru. In English, you don't normally say, like, in normal English, you don't say oh yasir. You just say hey, like, you just say yasir. You don't always say hey either, depending on the context, if it's formal or informal. So you can just translate it as yasir, comma. Yasir, comma. So in some of the newer translations of the Qur'an, you'll see it Written like this Instead of the old archaic Oh Yasir Do you get it? Right? In terms of meaning They're the same But it's just About a question of style
[SPEAKER_00] And what is In vogue And what is used nowadays Right? So anyways But Ya is when you're calling To somebody When you're talking to someone You want to get their attention So you call to them And you say Ya Okay? Now the rule for Ya Is that Generally If a word comes after Ya That's being called to And it becomes Dhamma Right? And no tanween You say يَاسِرٌ But when you say يَا Then you say يَا يَاسِرُ There's only one ضَمَّ يَا اللَّهُ يَا رَحْمَانُ يَا رَحِيمُ يَا مَلِكُ يَا قُدُّوسُ يَا سَلَامُ It only has one ضَمَّ That's the rule for it We don't have to go through it in detail It's pretty simple, right? Everybody got that? Okay هَذِهِ Okay Let's breeze through this lesson very quickly Right? So Hadihi, we already learned about Hadha and Dalika, right? They're part of which family? Quick, quick, quick, come on. I know you all want to go home. Ishaara. Huh? Ishaara, right?
[SPEAKER_00] They're always pointing fingers. They're judgmental, right? So Hadihi is similar to Hadha in a sense that it is? Singular. Singular, good. And? Close, right? But the difference between Hadha and Hadhi is one is male, one is female. That's very simple, right? Okay. So Hadi. We don't have to translate all these. I think it's pretty simple. Everybody got it? Hadi, right? 33. Actually, this is the last lesson, right? This is the last lesson? No. Yeah, it is the last lesson. That's the same lesson. Okay. So let's very, very quickly breeze through this lesson in five, seven minutes. What? Yeah, this is part of the test. This is on the test too, yes. Okay. Okay, this is Hamid's son and this is
[SPEAKER_00] Yasser's daughter, right? So, yeah, okay. Good, very good. Okay. One point to note over here is Waqifatun So the general rule is that Ta marboota Which is either written like this Or like this Depending on what letter comes before it So ta marboota is what indicates Towards something being feminine So now that's not only for names Or even for objects That's how we know it's a female But even for words that are describing a female You have to add this to it So you cannot tell somebody That's offensive If you're saying that they're A masculine So you would say You are beautiful So if you're talking to a female it will be By the way everything I say like this is a complete joke Just to keep you guys alive We
[SPEAKER_00] all know it's not permissible to do these things Even all the quahua house jokes I hope nobody goes there and actually Does these things It's completely impermissible It's completely wrong to mix like that So I just do it to keep you guys alive Because as you guys can see I'm not doing it You guys are literally dying in front of my eyes And like nobody's Since the beginning of the class Until now everybody just Sorry? We're practicing Yeah, okay So okay So okay Bintu Yasirin Waqifatun Right? So we're talking about Waqifatun means standing, right? So it's talking about Because it's talking about Bintu Yasir It's Waqifatun With the term al-buta Not Waqifun But when it was a male Ibn Hamidin Then it's Jalisun Right? If we were talking about a female, if we were talking about Bintu Hamidin, then it would be Jali Setun. That's the most important thing we learned in this lesson. Another thing here is Ha-Dha-Bnu Hamidin, right? Hamzatul Wasil. Can somebody remind me of the rule of Hamzatul Wasil?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, so if it's in the Yeah, sorry? Yeah, it's not that you don't pronounce it at all. In specific context, you don't pronounce it. So, yeah, if it's in the middle of Your sentence or you're saying something Then you don't pronounce it, you skip it It's silent But if it's in the beginning Then you do pronounce it And the harakah on it Will be based on what the word is So for example So the hamza in al is a hamzatul wasil So if it comes to the beginning It will be a fatha But ibn it has a kasra That also is hamzatul wasil but it has a kasra So it's not just a set harakah on hamzatul wasil It depends on the word So ism too, right? Ism means name It's a Hamzat al-Wassl So if you want to say What is your name? You say masmuka You don't say ma ismuka Okay? But if you're saying If it's in the middle If it's in the beginning of a word And you say ismu Ismu talibi Abdul Samad for example Right? So ism
[SPEAKER_00] you pronounce the Hamzah Right? That's the rule for Hamzat al-Wassl Hopefully everybody got that inshallah Now how do you know If you're reading something And you see Normally we would call it an alif When we learn But it's a hamza So how do we know if this is A hamza tul wasal Or what's called a hamza tul qatar Which is the hamza that's pronounced in every context Yeah good Not harakah but specifically the hamza The ones that have a hamza On top or on the bottom Right That's called the hamza tul qatar You don't have to know the name but It means that it's not a hamza tul wasal You got that But if it doesn't have a Hamza On the top or the bottom Then that means it is a Hamza tul wasal Okay So that's how you know The difference between the two Understand? Yeah Okay I mean technically This is not This is a Dajweed rule anyways Or like a reading rule But we're just learning it here anyways Because that's part of Learning the language Okay Aydan is a new word Which means also Okay
[SPEAKER_00] Ahiya Aydan Muhandisa tun Again Since she's a female engineer You say Muhandisa tun Not Muhandisa And طبيبت is a female doctor So you really know طبيب means doctor So we just add a Tamir Bhutan and it becomes female سيارة من هاده Whose car is this سيارة مديري ما هاده هاده مكوات Okay, new vocabulary words لمن هاده Okay, now this word لام Right? It's a harf الجر Right? ل Right? And we already mentioned it means For or belongs to Right? So To whom belongs this car? Right? Or whose car is this? هَذِي لِخَالِدٍ So just remember that lamb makes the word after it كَسْرَ Okay, as we mentioned in Surah Fatiha Right in the beginning الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ Right? All praise belongs to Allah Right? So that's why it's لِلَّهِ It's كَسْرَ because the lamb before The loveful Jalal before Allah is حَرْفُ الْجَرْ So
[SPEAKER_00] it makes the word of Allah's name كَسْرَ Okay? Let's see anything else I'm not going to read the whole lesson Just seeing if there's anything else Relevant over here جمية جدن Right So جدن always has a fatha on it Right No matter what the context is And it means very Right So if you want to emphasize something Then you say This is very blank Right Here جمية جدن It is very beautiful Okay And you can use this for any Sort of Adjective Right Something that's very big, for example It's very big, right? So any adjective, you just add jidden And you have emphasized it Understand? Okay Okay, last thing and then we'll end it off Inshallah right here, right? Two things, sorry
[SPEAKER_00] So one is that Qidrun, right? So generally we mention that To know if an object is female or male We just look at if it has This tamar buta at the end Right? That's a general rule However there are exceptions There are some nouns Which look like they're male Because they don't have any tamar buta at the end But they're actually female Right? How do we know they're female? There's no way for us to know except By learning it Through, you know, reading of text Or for a teacher telling us Or hearing an Arab saying it And when we say hearing the Arab saying it We're not talking about The general Arab today Because they don't really speak fushah And they don't really keep these things in mind When they're speaking, right? What does that mean, fushah? Fushah means, like I mean, literally it means The eloquent, but basically it just means proper Arabic With all the rules Fushah
[SPEAKER_00] So like If you start speaking to an Arab brother And he starts like Speaking back to you super fast And like breaking all the rules that you learned Then know that he's not speaking Fuzha Right Yeah So anyways So when we say the Arabs They were talking about the true Arabs Of the past who Or even today if there's any Arab brothers Or who know the language properly So that's how we will know Otherwise, there's no way for us to know. Write what? Fusha. So, like, if you start speaking to... This happened to me a few times, where, like, some brother asked me, oh, you speak Arabic? I'm like, yes. And I'm like, okay. And they start asking me a question in Ammiya. And, like, sometimes I can figure it out. A lot of times I can figure it out. But sometimes, like, you know, the way they speak it, just like a completely different language. Like, so then I'm just like, oh, I only speak Fusha, right? So then they'll understand,
[SPEAKER_00] like, oh, okay, they'll understand why you don't. So if you ever get in a situation where you think, oh, Masha, I know some Arabic, and you start speaking, and they just, like, come back to you with that, then you just be like, oh, sorry, sorry, I only speak. أنا فقط أتكلم الفصحة. Right? Just be like that. Okay. So Qidr, right? So there's some words that are female, even though they look like they're male because they don't have ta marboota. Right? So you can only know them by learning, by somebody telling you. Otherwise, there's no way you can figure that out. Okay? So I advise that you should probably make a list of those words as you come along them, right? That'll help you, right? Yesterday in the Tafsir class, I mentioned one word because can anybody who was in the Tafsir class? There's only like two brothers or three brothers here that were part of the Tafsir class. Anybody? In relation to what? That looks like male, but it's actually female. What now? Shows? Nafs, right? So the word nafs is another word that it looks like it's male. It doesn't have a tanween Sorry, it doesn't have a tamar
[SPEAKER_00] buta But it's actually female So nafs is If it was male Then it would have been But because it's female So there are certain words that They seem to be male Because they don't have a tamar buta But they actually are female You have to learn what they are I advise writing a list Anybody have a list of the words you mentioned in class? Okay, what were they? Shamsun, okay. Shams is a female word even though it has no term. Then? Jahannam, good. Nar, good. Qiyama has term. Jannah has term. Dunya, good. Qidrun, good. Sorry, Sabilun, good. Sabil means the way or path, right? طريق is another one طريق sorry
[SPEAKER_00] yeah but those are the rule for that is coming but it wouldn't technically be part of this category yes okay so these are the words we should just know that these are words that are female even though it looks like they're male okay last rule inshallah then we're finished we'll end off over here which is the rule of body parts right can anybody remind me what that rule is yeah so generally uh body parts that have one part like for example a nose you only have one nose right you don't have multiple noses um and eye i'm sorry not eyes um your forehead I'm sorry, forehead doesn't count. What was it? Fem. Yeah, mouth, right? And other body parts, which you only have one of, those are going to be male, right? Now, other body parts, which have two counterparts, like yed, for example.
[SPEAKER_00] By the way, just to clarify, we've translated yed as hand, right? You can do that. Sometimes yed is used for hand. But technically, yed is the whole arm, right? The whole arm is called yed. That's just something to point out. Because when we translated yad, I mentioned hand But to be more accurate, yad includes a whole arm Okay So anyways, so yad is Even though it looks like it's male Because it doesn't have tabar buta But because it is a body part that has two counterparts Therefore you use It's a female, right? So you say Same thing with ayn, right? The eye is female So you say Same thing with rijl Rijl means leg, right? So, this is a leg. So, that's the rule for body parts and whether they're masculine or feminine. All right? Everybody got that? Okay. And that's pretty much it. Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00] Yadun, yes. Hadih Yadun. Yadun or Yadun? Yadun. Yeah. But that's male, right? If it's female, it's only one dama. No, it's only for names. only for female names like Fauti, Matu, Zainabu not for female regular nouns yeah is there another word for just hand? is there another word for just hand? yeah, Kaff Kaff are we doing like numbers like large numbers? yeah, that's coming inshallah yeah everything mashallah this book is very very comprehensive it has pretty much everything alhamdulillah that we need to know okay any other questions? otherwise we can end I haven't really thought about how I'm going to make the test yet But
[SPEAKER_00] Like I might ask in different ways I might just say for example Highlight all the mudhafullah filay's in this Or I might even just give you A few sentences and say okay Explain what grammar rules are in these sentences That you learned so far So you have to like take Okay there's hadha So you talk about what is hadha And you know this indicates that it's one singular And this that that And there's mudhaf mudhaf filay So you have to explain Okay it has only It doesn't have tanwin or al and this and that So I might do something like that Or I might just say List the five rules of mudhaf mudhaf filay For example right Or I might just say You know I'm leaving it open right So I want you guys to study Basically that's why I'm saying that Are we going to have the family names on the test? Sorry? Family names on the test Family names? That might be extra credit Because I mentioned multiple times That it's not absolutely necessary To know the Arabic names for them For like for example Harf al-Athf Harf al-Jar I mean Harf al-Jar we should know Mudhaf
[SPEAKER_00] al-Athfi we should also know But others like for example Adawatu al-Istifham Things like that It's not absolutely necessary To know the Arabic names But like I said Eventually if you plan on joining us till the end then you're going to have to know it eventually so you might as well know it now so because of that I'm not going to test it in the official test but it might be extra credit so we'll have one more I'm trying to think of how exactly we'll do it we'll have one more review session before the test after the break because we're probably going to forget everything over the break if you don't study so we'll have a quick review session On the 13th We can decide how to do it together If you guys want You can just ask questions Or you guys can just sit here And review yourselves Right? Or if you have anything You want me to explain And I can re-explain again But we won't have I just wanted to have mercy on you And not have the test right when we come back So I'll give you guys a date Where we come and sit Where we study together Review together Then on the 15th We will have the test Inshallah
[SPEAKER_00] Alhamdulillah Alhamdulillah Amin I mean, I mean, I mean, I mean, it's not okay. All right, subhanallah, bi-hamdhi, subhanakallah, bi-hamdhi, kanashdu allah ilaha ilaha ilaha indah al-astaghfirullah atubu ilai, subhanallah, rabbika, rabbil izzati, ammasifun, wassalamun, alhamdulillahi, rabbil amman.